Guide to the Peruvian Collection, 1583-1892 RL.01017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Peruvian collection
1583-1892
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Odriozola, Manuel de, 1804-1889
RL.01017
6 Linear Feet
circa 47 Items; 21 Volumes
Collection contains papers relating to Peru, roughly falling into three groups centering around commerce and industry, literary activities, and religious and social history. Includes papers (1786-1787) containing information on the mining of mercury; poems of Juan de Valle y Caviedes in 17th century script; poems by Antonio de Solís; one volume of Documentos históricos, collected by Manuel de Odriozola; three Documentos literarios from contemporary publications, among them a compilation of the papers of Peruvian viceroys and others (1580-1818); a paper relating to witchcraft and idolatry in Peru; papers (1772-1773) of the Provincial Council at Lima, containing the core of the debate within the Catholic Church on the modernization of learning which Charles III attempted to foist upon the empire; a copy of the proceso of Mariano Tupac Amaro; and material relating to politics and the industrial development of Peru and neighboring countries during the 19th century.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The materials in the Peruvian Collection were acquired by Duke University from 1933 to 1948.
Collection Overview
This collection of heterogeneous material, generally relating to the colonial period of Peru, falls roughly into three groups centering around commerce and industry, literary activity, and religious and social history. Several manuscripts in the first group contain information on the mining of mercury, 1786-1787. Literary materials include the poems of Caviedes in the seventeenth century script useful for correcting errors in the copies published by Ricardo Palma; a copy of iconoclastic and mysterious poems by Antonio de Solís; one cuaderno of the Documentos históricos collected by Manuel de Odriozola; and three Documentos literarios from contemporary publications. Among the Items relating to religion and social history are a compilation of the papers of Peruvian viceroys and others, 1580-1818; an expediente concerning witchcraft and idolatry in Peru; original papers on the modernization of learning which Charles III attempted to impose upon the empire; copy of the proceso of Mariano Tupac Amaru; and a booklet, 1794, describing the founding and development of Quito, Ecuador.
Some of these Items, formerly the property of Manuel de Odriozola, the Peruvian literary historian who brought together this collection, are listed in the Cátalogo de la Biblioteca Peruana Propiedad de Dn. Francisco Perez de Velasco (Lima, 1918). Rubén Vargas Ugarte, S. J., describes some of these manuscripts in Manuscritos Peruanos en las Bibliotecas de América (Buenos Aires, 1945, pp. 230-243) which is volume IV of his Biblioteca Peruana (Lima, 1935- ). John Tate Lanning, James B. Duke Professor of History, also mentioned these manuscripts in his article "The Hispanic Collection" published in Gnomon, Essays for the Dedication of the William R. Perkins Library (Duke Unlversity, April 15 and 16, 1970).
This guide to the collection is the result of extensive recataloging in which, for the first time, considerable attention has been given to analyzing the content of the manuscripts. The descriptions of many of the manuscripts have been enlarged, and, in some cases, author and title information has been changed or refined. Many entries have been added to the card catalog based upon these new descriptions. Copies of these cards have been included in this guide in order to provide additional means of access to the contents of the collection.
Spain -- Colonies -- America -- Administration; Quito (Ecuador) -- History; Peru -- History -- Sources; Peru -- History -- 1829-1919; Peru -- Intellectual life; Perú -- History -- 1548-1820; Peru -- Commerce; Witchcraft -- Perú; Viceroys -- South America; Peruvian literature.; Mercury mines and mining -- Perú; Idolatry -- Perú; Palma, Ricardo; Solís, Antonio de; Valle y Caviedes, Juan del; Catholic Church -- Peru.; Tupac Amaru, Mariano; Odriozola, Manuel de, 1804-1889
- Peruvian collection, 1583-1892
  - Guide to the collection (Box 1)
  - Eguidio a su amigo. Diálogo. La Naturaleza, y Hijo. Libro 2º de Mangeto ? f. 236. (Box 2, Ms 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    n. p., n. d. 50 folios.
    A hypothetical dialogue between nature and her son.
  - Montero Bolaños de los Reyes, Francisco Xavier. Papeles que pertenecen a Francisco Xavier Montero Bolaños de los Reyes. (Box 2, Ms 2)
    Caracas, 1765-1770. 72 pages.
    Petition, auto, and testimonials concerning the purity of race (limpieza de sangre) of Francisco Montero Bolaños de los Reyes. Caracas, 1765-1770.
    The purity of race (limpieza de sangre) was documented by testimonials demonstrating that the person was not a descendant of Moors, Jews, heretics, or penitenciados (persons punished by the Inquisition). This documentation was a prerequisite in Spain and its colonies in order to be admitted into a corporation, school or university, to practice a profession, or a trade, and to get married. A law of May 16, 1865, abolished this requirement for marriage and for admission into the public service, and it was definitively abolished by the 27th article of the 1869 Constitution, and the 15th article of the 1876 Constitution (in force).
    This manuscript is an important source for the study of social or economic discrimination against racial or ethnic groups in Spain and its colonies till the end of the XIX century.
  - Libro manual de entrada, salida y existencia de los azogues que sa hallan en los almacenes de ellos desde el l. de Enero de 1787 haste fin de Diciembre de el. Por Francisco Angel Bravo de Rueda. (Box 2, Ms 3)
    1787. 19 folios.
    This original manuscript is an important source of information on mercury production in the Huancavelica Dept. and in the province of Huarochiri, Peru. Information about the dates of arrival and departure from the warehouses, the weight, value, geographical source, and name of owners or shippers of the mercury are specified. Reports appear throughout the year, and a summary of figures for the year is given.
  - Peru (Viceroyalty). Expediente concerning witchcraft and idolatry in Peru. (Box 3, Ms 4)
    1700. 188 folios.
    This expediente contains two royal cédulas issued by Charles III and Charles IV, kings of Spain and the Indies. One cédula was issued on June 25, 1783, at Aranjuéz, and the other, on Oct. 9, 1789, at San Lorenzo del Real. In both cédulas, the Bishop of Trujillo in Peru, Don Baltasar J. Martinez Compañón, is ordered not to relent on his work of converting the Indians into the Christian faith. This expediente also contains an edict of the Bishop and correspondence between him and others under his jurisdiction in relation to the same matter (ff. 1-10). This manuscript is notable because most of its contents are the original records of a trial for witchcraft and idolatry conducted against Salvador Bautista, Nicolás Bautista, Julián Bautista, Margarita Chuquipul (Salvador's wife), Petrona Huilca (Nicolás's wife), and María Paysic. Juán de Roxas, priest and vicar of the Doctrina of Atún Luya, was the acting judge and Blas de la Encidna was the acting notary (ff. 11-188). The trial began on Feb. 28, 1789, and the last record dated was July 9, 1790. It took place at the asiento of San Juán de Lamúd, but the defendants were from San Pedro de Cuemal. Between March 3 and May 11, 1789, 55 witnesses were examined; they were relatives and neighbors of the defendants and almost all of them certified their depositions (ff. 15-120). Confessions were taken from the defendants (ff. 120-150), and the prosecution and the defense presented their petitions (ff. 151-156). The sentence was pronounced on June 3, 1789 (ff. 157-158). The Royal Justice sentenced Salvador and Nicolás Bautista and Maria Paysíc to be whipped through the streets over a packsaddle, with a coronet on their heads and their backs naked. Petrona Huilca, Margarita Chuquipul, and Julián Bautista were sentenced to be feathered, to wear a coronet on their heads, and to serve as shield-bearers of the other offenders, their punishment being left to the discretion of the executioner. While the sentence was publicly performed, all the idols and instruments used by the defendants in their rites were thrown into a bonfire. Immediately they were expatriated to the Province of Caxamarca, confined to a house of correction in perpetuity, and obliged to do hard work with rations but without salary for a landowner who would provide them with the necessary prisons until their death. Their houses were demolished and exorcised, and great crosses were placed on the lots and on the caves, rocks, and temples they had used for their rites.
    The expediente includes the estimates of the cost of the trial (f. 165), the inventory, valuation, and the sale by public auction of the properties of Salvador and Nicolás Bautista (ff. 166-184), as well as the accounts of the trustees, with credits and debits (ff. 185-188).
  - Perú (Viceroyalty). Testironio de los autos seguidos contra Mariano Túpac Amaro y Andrés Mendigure sobre atribuirseles la reincidencia en la revelidn Año de 1783. Real Sala del Crimen. Escribano de Cámara, Don Clemente Castellanos, 1780-1783. (Box 4, Ms 5)
    Lima, Perú, 1780-1783. 372 folios.
    Typescript from the original in a volume of Manuscritos varios desposited in the Archivo Nacional del Perú, containing testimonies on the trial for relapse into rebellion, against Mariano Tupac Amaru and Andrés Mendigure, son and nephew of José Gabriel Túpac Amaru, leader of the Indian insurrection against the Spaniards in Perú during 1780-1781. These testimonies are not a complete record of the trial. They are divided into six cuadernos and one expediente with a total of 372 consecutive folios. The half title is Rebelión de Túpac Amaro. Tomo. I. The cuadernos contain correspondence between the Viceroy Agustín Jaureaui, the Bishop of Cuzco, members of the Túpac Amaru family, and other civilian, military and religious dignataries, in relation to the Túpac Amaru Insurrection. The cuadernos also contain depositions of witnesses on the trial against Mariano Túpac Amaru and Andrés Mendigure. The expediente contains the claims of José Antonio Escale, Relator de la Real Sala del Crimen, and Clemente Castellanos, Escribano of the same court, requesting to be paid for their work on the trial against Mariano Túpac Amaru and Andrés Mendigure. Túpac Amaru and Mendigure were sentenced to expartiation in Spain, the first died during the trip, and Mendigure perished in a shipwreck off the coast of Portugal. For further information see:
    La rebelión de Túpac Amaru by Daniel Valcárcel Esparza, Mexico, 1947 (p. 167-168).
  - Documentos reservados en los Autos Criminales contra Mariano Túpac Amaro y Andrés Mendigure sobre reincidencias y posteriores excesos cometidos de resultas de la nueva sublevación acaesida en los altos de Marcapata Provincia de Quispicanchi. (Box 5, Ms 5A)
    Lima Perú, 1780-1783. 364 p., 249-333 p.
    Typewritten copy from the original in a volume of manuscript documents deposited in the Biblioteca y Archivo Nacional, Lima, Perú. Bound in a book entitled Rebelión de Tupac Amaru, Tomo II (313 folios).
    These confidential documents contain correspondence between the Viceroy Agustín Jauregui, and some members of the Túpac Amaru family, and also with military, ecclesiastical and civilian dignataries. Included are also other records of the trial against Mariano Túpac Amaru and Andrés Mendigures. It is a valuable source of information for researchers interested in the study of the Túpac Amaru insurrection in Perú.
  - Documentos reservados en los autos criminales contra Mariano Túpac Amaro y Andrés Mendigure sobre reincidencia y posteriores excesos cometidos de resultas de la nueva sublevación acaesida en los altos de Marcapata Provincia de Quispicanchi. Tomo segundo. (Box 5, Ms 5B)
    n. p. Typescript, n. d. 178 folios.
    This volume is an incomplete typescript copy of MS. No. 5 containing only information as far as page 305 of MS. No. 5A.
  - Memorias relatives a la sublevación del Casique de Tunga-Suca José Gabriel Tupac-Amaro su consecuencias y fin de este estraordinario suceso cuyo acaecimiento empezó el año de 1780 (Box 5, Ms 5C)
    Lima, Perú, 1780. [1], 173 p.
    Negative microfilm of typed copy in the Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley.
    Motives or reasons of the insurrection of the Indians of high Perú under the leadership of Don José Gabriel Túpac-Amaru Casique de Tunga-Suca.
    Transferred to Newspapers and Microfilms Department.
  - Pizarro, Gonzalo (1502-1548), et al. Transcripts of a collection of 19 letters, 1547-1548, written during the rebellion of Gonzalo Pizarro in Perú (1546-1548). (Box 6, Ms 6)
    v. p., 1547-1548. Pages 378-505.
    Transcripts of a collection of 19 letters, 1547-1548, written during the rebellion of Gonzalo Pizarro in Perú (1546-1548) by Pedro de la Gasca (1493-1567), Gonzalo Pizarro (1502-1548), Philip II (1527-1598) as Prince, Lorenzo de Albana (d. 1571), and Diego Cepeda (d. 1550). These letters were transcribed in a very legible hand and are related to Gonzalo Pizarro's rebellion that ended with his defeat and execution as a traitor to King Charles V by Pedro de la Gasca at Xaquixaguana, Perú, on April 10, 1548.
  - Odriozola, Manuel de (1804-1889). Colección de poesías modernas. Recogidas por Manuel de Odriozola. Cuaderno 5º. Principiado en Lima el 1º. de Marzo de 1849 y concluido en la Hacienda de la Mejorada en Huancayo, Abril, Domingo 19 de 1857. 101ff., [2] ff. indice. (Box 6, Ms 7)
    Perú, 1849-1857. 103 folios.
    Selections of poetry assembled by Odriozola consisting chiefly of sonnets, several lyrics, and some burlesque forms. This volume includes: a sonnet of the Spanish poet Francisco de Miranda y Vengóa (d. 1857); some poems published by El Comercio (1845) and signed by Z., apparently the pseudonym of the Peruvian poet Felipe de Pardo y Aliaga (1806-1868); a short story published by La Bolsa (1841) and written by Manuel Ascencio Segura (1805-1871), another Peruvian author; a poem of the famous Colombian poet Rafael Pombo (1833-1912) published at Lima by El Heraldo on Jan. 5, 1856, under the pseudonym Edda, and some other poems written by unknown writers.
  - Odriozola, Manuel de (1804-1889). Copias de varies poesías. Cuaderno l ro. año de 1837. (Box 6, Ms 7A)
    Perú, 1837. 56 ff., [1] f., index.
    This volume also includes: some poems of Felipe Pardo Aliaga (1806-1868); a short poem adapted to music ( letrilla) written by Manuel Ascencio Segura (1805-1871); a ballad by an anonymous author; and a poem of José Joaquín Larriva (1780-1832).
    Manuscript 7a does not have Odriozola's name on it. It is attributed to him by Perez de Velasco in his Catalogo de la Biblioteca Peruana (p. 141). In addition, the handwriting of No. 7a is similiar to that in No. 7 and in other manuscripts that have Odriozola's name as their compiler.
  - Odriozola, Manuel de (1804-1889). Cartas de Heloysa y Abelardo. ff. 1-23. Added t. p.: Poesías antiguas y modernas. Cuaderno 4º. Principiado en el año de 1837 y concluido en 22 de Marzo de 1840. (Box 6, Ms 7B)
    Perú. ff. 24-54, [1] f., index.
    The majority of the poems in this volume were transcribed from the initial issues of El Mercurio Peruano (1791). Included are copies of décimas (a Spanish stanza consisting of ten verses of eight syllables), one octava (a poetical composition of eight lines of eleven syllables) written by the Peruvian poet F. M. Miranda at Trujillo, Perú, in Feb., 1836, letters between Heloise and Abelard, and a few poetical works by unknown writers.
    Manuscript 7b does not have Odriozola's name on it. It is attributed to him by Perez de Velasco in his Catalogo de la Biblioteca Peruana (p. 141). In addition, the handwriting of No. 7b is similar to that in No. 7 and in other manuscripts that have Odriozola's name as their compiler.
  - Fein, John M. Una Versión Desconocida de un Poema de Pombo. (Box 6, Ms 7C)
    Medellín, Colombia, 1953. 1 p.
    Newspaper article by Dr. Fein in El Colombiano, Suplemento (May 3, 1953), on one of the poems in MS. No. 7 of the Peruvian Collection.
  - Perú (Viceroyalty). Documentos inéditos. (Box 6, Ms 8)
    v. p., 1580-1818. 4 p., 182 folios.
    Typewritten table of contents of the 31 manuscript documents bound in this volume. 4 p.
    The manuscripts are listed below in the order of appearance in this volume. Each manuscript has its own pagination, if any.
    1. Act siqned Oct. 24, 1580, by Viceroy Francisco de Toledo appointing Diego de Valero Corregidor of the Valley of Ica and its District, and commissioning Antonio Vadillo to take residence there. It is followed by the testimony of the oath given by Valero at Chincha on Nov. 13 of the same year. The appointment was limited to one year with a salary of 600 pesos. ff. 119-122.
    2. Questionnaire. Questions that the Judge of Residence of the Villa de Santa and its Partido, Diego G. de Ocampo, will ask the witnesses giving deposition on the secret information against Francisco de Mendieta who has been Corregidor of that Partido and against his officers and ministers. Followed by instructions and ordinances for Corregidores signed by Viceroy Francisco de Toledo May 30, 1580. Followed by a testimonial that the instructions and ordinances were seen by the Justice and Regiment of the City of the Kings (Lima) July 1, 1580. And a testimonial that was also read to the Caciques and Principales of the town of Nuestra Señora del Rosario de Guarmey Aug. 15, 1580, translated by the Indian Antonio de Guamán. ff. 24-68.
    3. Ordinances for Corregidores given at Seville on June 9, 1500, by King Ferdinand and Queen Isabella and enforced in Perú and signed by Viceroy Francisco de Toledo at the appointment of Gabriel de la Reguera as Corregidor of the city of León de Huánuco. ff. 1-24, [12] ff. undated
    4. Act signed by Viceroy Garcia Hurtado de Mendoza on March 8, 1590, ordering the payment to surgeon Francisco Velázquez de Chavez from the funds of the community of the Repartimiento de Mama for the medical care given to the Indians during the epidemic of that region. 1 f.
    5. Royal Cédula signed at Madrid on Dec. 5, 1603, by King Philip III commanding the Viceroy of Peru, Gaspar de Zuñiga Azevedo y Fonseca, Conde de Monterrey, to execute the order given to his predecessor, Viceroy Luis de Velasco, Marqués de Salinas, in relation to providing the needs of four Jesuit missionaries, residents in Santa Cruz de la Sierra. 1 f.
    6. Decree signed by Viceroy Juán de Mendoza y Luna, Marqués de Montes Claros, on July 12, 1615, granting a loan of 8500 pesos to Gaspar Rodriguez de Castro from the funds paid by the Indians to the community. 1 f.
    7. Royal Cédula signed at San Lorenzo on Aug. 27, 1617, by King Philip III confirming the Encomienda de Indios granted by the Viceroy of Peru, Juán de Mendoza y Luna, Marqués de Montes Claros, to Diego Peñalosa y Briceño for two generations, on condition that he contribute one-third of his profits to the royal funds of the city of Lima. 1 f.
    8. Act by the Royal Audiencia of Lima presided over by and signed by Viceroy Luis Geronimo Fernandez de Cabrera y Bobadilla, Conde de Chinchón, on Sept. 6, 1633, granting loans of 374 pesos from the funds of the Indians of the Repartimiento de Lunaguana to Alonso de Torres Romero and to Luis Sánchez de Garro for the payment of their tribute from one-third of San Juan that year. 1 f.
    9. Instructions signed by Viceroy Pedro de Toledo y Leiva, Marqués de Mancera, on Nov. 6, 1643, for the deposition of accounts and Residencia to be given by Pedro de Valladares, recently appointed Corregidor of the City of Piura. ff. 1-24
    10. Act signed by Viceroy Pedro de Toledo y Leiva, Marqués de Mancera, on Aug. 17, 1644, commanding the Administrator of funds of the Censo de Indios de Lima to deliver to the Fiscal Protector de Naturales the amount of pesos written in the adjunct certificate. f. 29
    11. Ordinances signed by Viceroy Pedro de Toledo y Leiva, Marqués de Mancera, on Aug. 27, 1644, directing Geronimo de Palma y Mayorga to observe and execute them while performing his duties as Justicia Mayor of the Province of Condesuyos. ff. 9-46.
    12. Royal Cédula signed by King Charles II at Buen Retiro on Feb. 12, 1677, addressed to the Viceroy and to the members of the Royal Audiencia of Lima reminding them about the oath of secrecy and confidentiality to observe while performing their duties. Followed by the testimony that the Cédula was read during the May 16, 1678, meeting of the Real Acuerdo. 2 ff.
    13. Letter signed by Queen Mariana at Madrid on Dec., 1665, addressed to the Archbishop of Lima requesting a donation for the Spanish government that was in dire economic straits. The last four lines were handwritten by the Queen who was the wife of King Philip IV and the mother of King Charles II. f. 324.
    14. Letter of Censure signed by the Archbishop of Lima, Pedro de Villagómez, on Dec. 29, 1659, demanding the return of a sequestered slave. 1 f.
    15. Letter of Censure signed by the members of the Cabildo Eclesiástico Metropolitano de Lima on March 18, 1672, asking for the return of 3,000 pesos taken from the home of Simón Vaez Enriquez. 1 f.
    16. Decree signed by Viceroy Melchor de Navarra y Rocafull, Duque de la Palata, on July 19, 1689, granting a loan of 5,000 pesos from the funds of Caja de Censos to the funds of la Comunidad to repair damages at the Cathedral of Lima caused by the 1685 earthquake. 1 f.
    17. Order of payment of the Real Audiencia de Lima presided over and signed by Viceroy Melchor de Navarra y Rocafull, Duque de la Palata, on Sept. 1, 1688, ordering the Caja de Censos to pay 125 pesos to the lawyer Francisco de Rojas y Acevedo for his services to that institution during 6 months. 1 f.
    18. Letter of Censure signed by the Archbishop of Lima, Melchor de Liñán y Cisneros, on June 10, 1694, demanding the return of a sequestered black slave to her owner, Fabián de Viñas y Coca. 1 f.
    19. A decree signed by the Archbishop of Lima, Melchor de Liñán y Cisneros, on March 23, 1691. Archbishop Cisneros was Viceroy of Perú from 1678 to 1681 when he was replaced at the viceroyalty by the Duque de la Palata, but he remained in Lima as Archbishop and as a member of the Royal Council. 1 f.
    20. Royal Cédula signed by King Philip V at Madrid on Feb. 19, 1714, demanding the Real Audiencia de Lima to see that the Juzgado de Bienes de Difuntos delivers all the properties that belonged to Fr. Pablo de Villanueva as ordered by the royal cédula. 1 f.
    21. Seven letters signed by Viceroy José de Armendáriz, Marqués de Castelfuerte, addressed to the Corregidor de Canas y Canches, Miguel de Santistevan, between June, 1724, and July, 1732. 7 ff.
    22. Royal Cédula signed by King Charles III at Aranjuéz on May 20, 1768, commanding the Tribunal de Cuentas (Court of Accounts) not to charge the Corregidores with Derecho de Tiras (cost of courts) for the arrangement of their accounts. 2 ff.